<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<node name="/" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.ModemManager.Modem.Gsm.Ussd">
    <method name="Initiate">
      <tp:docstring>
        Sends a USSD command string to the network initiating a USSD session.
        When the request is handled by the network, the method returns the
        response or an appropriate error.  The network may be awaiting further
        response from the ME after returning from this method and no new command
        can be initiated until this one is cancelled or ended.
      </tp:docstring>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.Async" value=""/>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_modem_gsm_ussd_initiate"/>
      <arg name="command" type="s" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The command to start the USSD session with.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="reply" type="s" direction="out">
        <tp:docstring>
          The network response to the command which started the USSD session.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <method name="Respond">
      <tp:docstring>
        Respond to a USSD request that is either initiated by the mobile network,
        or that is awaiting further input after Initiate() was called.
      </tp:docstring>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.Async" value=""/>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_modem_gsm_ussd_respond"/>
      <arg name="response" type="s" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The response to network-initiated USSD command, or a response to a
          request for further input.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="reply" type="s" direction="out">
        <tp:docstring>
          The network reply to this response to the network-initiated USSD
          command.  The reply may require further responses.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <method name="Cancel">
      <tp:docstring>
        Cancel an ongoing USSD session, either mobile or network initiated.
      </tp:docstring>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.Async" value=""/>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_modem_gsm_ussd_cancel"/>
    </method>

    <property name="State" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Indicates the state of any ongoing USSD session.  Values may be one of
        the following: "idle" (no active session), "active" (a session is active
        and the mobile is waiting for a response), "user-response" (the network
        is waiting for the client's response, which must be sent using Respond()).
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="NetworkNotification" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Contains any network-initiated request to which no USSD response is
        required.  When no USSD session is active, or when there is no network-
        initiated request, this property will be a zero-length string.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="NetworkRequest" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Contains any pending network-initiated request for a response.  Client
        should call Respond() with the appropriate response to this request.
        When no USSD session is active, or when there is no pending
        network-initiated request, this property will be a zero-length string.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
