<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<node name="/" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.ModemManager.Modem.Location">
    <tp:docstring>
      This interface allows devices to provide location information to client
      applications.  Not all devices can provide this information, or even if
      they do, they may not be able to provide it while a data session is
      active.
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Capabilities" type="u" access="read" tp:type="MM_MODEM_LOCATION_CAPABILITIES">
      <tp:docstring>
        Location capabilities of the device.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Enabled" type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        TRUE if location information gathering is enabled for this device, FALSE
        if it is disabled. When disabled, the device will not provide location
        information.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="Enable">
      <tp:docstring>
        Enable or disable location information gathering.  This method may
        require the client to authenticate itself.  This method may also cause
        any necessary functionality of the mobile be be turned on, including
        enabling the modem device itself.
      </tp:docstring>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.Async" value=""/>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_modem_location_enable"/>
      <arg name="enable" type="b" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          TRUE to enable location information gathering, FALSE to disable.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="signal_location" type="b" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          When enabling location information gathering, this argument controls
          whether the device emits signals with new location information or not.
          When signals are emitted, any client application (including malicious
          ones!) can listen for location updates unless D-Bus permissions
          restrict these signals from certain users.  If further security is
          desired, this argument can be set to FALSE to disable location
          updates via D-Bus signals and require applications to call
          authenticated APIs (like GetLocation) to get location information.
          This argument is ignored when disabling location information
          gathering.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <method name="GetLocation">
      <tp:docstring>
        Return current location information, if any.  This method may require
        the client to authenticate itself.
      </tp:docstring>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.Async" value=""/>
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_modem_location_get_location"/>
      <arg name="Location" type="a{uv}" direction="out" tp:type="Location_Information_Map">
        <tp:docstring>
          Dict of available location information when location information
          gathering is enabled.  If the modem supports multiple location types
          it may return more than one here.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <property name="SignalsLocation" type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        TRUE if location updates will be emitted via D-Bus signals, FALSE
        if location updates will not be emitted.  See the Enable method for
        more information.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Location" type="a{uv}" access="read" tp:type="Location_Information_Map">
      <tp:docstring>
        Dict of available location information when location information
        gathering is enabled.  If the modem supports multiple location types
        it may return more than one here.  Note that if the device was told
        not to emit updated location information when location information
        gathering was initially enabled, this property may not return
        any location information for security reasons.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <tp:mapping name="Location_Information_Map">
      <tp:docstring>
        A mapping from location type to type-specific location information.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" name="Type" tp:type="MM_MODEM_LOCATION_CAPABILITIES">
        <tp:docstring>
          Identifies the type and format of the associated location information.
          Contrary to the value description, this is not a bitfield but uses the
          same values as the MM_MODEM_LOCATION_CAPABILITIES bitfield.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="v" name="Data">
        <tp:docstring>
          Contains type-specific location information.  See the documentation for
          each type for a description of its data format.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>

    <tp:flags name="MM_MODEM_LOCATION_CAPABILITIES" value-prefix="MM_MODEM_LOCATION_CAPABILITY" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="UNKNOWN" value="0x0">
        <tp:docstring><p>Unknown or no capabilties.</p></tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="GPS_NMEA" value="0x1">
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>For capability reporting, indicates the device is capable of
            providing GPS NMEA-format location information.</p>

          <p>For location reporting, devices supporting this capability return
            a string containing one or more NMEA sentences (D-Bus signature 's').
            The manager will cache the most recent NMEA sentence of each type for
            a period of time not less than 30 seconds.  When reporting multiple
            NMEA sentences, sentences shall be separated by an ASCII Carriage
            Return and Line Feed (&lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt;) sequence.
          </p>
          <p>
            For example, if the device sends a $GPRMC sentence immediately
            followed by a $GPGGA sentence, the reported location string would be
            (where of course the &lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt; is replaced with the actual
            ASCII CR (0x0D) and LF (0x0A) control characters):
            <pre>
              $GPRMC,134523.92,V,,,,,,,030136,,,N*73&lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt;$GPGGA,,,,,,0,00,0.5,,M,0.0001999,M,0.0000099,0000*45
            </pre>
            If the device sends a new $GPRMC three seconds later, the new $GPRMC
            replaces the previously received $GPRMC sentence, and the updated
            string would be:
            <pre>
              $GPRMC,134526.92,V,,,,,,,030136,,,N*76&lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt;$GPGGA,,,,,,0,00,0.5,,M,0.0001999,M,0.0000099,0000*45
            </pre>
            If the device then sends a $GPGSA sentence about 5 seconds later, the
            $GPGSA sentence is added to the string (since no $GPGSA sentence was
            previously received in this session), the updated string would be:
            <pre>
              $GPRMC,134526.92,V,,,,,,,030136,,,N*76&lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt;$GPGGA,,,,,,0,00,0.5,,M,0.0001999,M,0.0000099,0000*45&lt;CR&gt;&lt;LF&gt;$GPGSA,A,1,,,,,,,,,,,,,1.1,0.5,1.0*34
            </pre>
            The manager may discard any cached sentences older than 30 seconds.
          </p>
          <p>This allows clients to read the latest positioning data as soon as
            possible after they start, even if the device is not providing
            frequent location data updates.
          </p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="GSM_LAC_CI" value="0x2">
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>For capability reporting, indicates the device is capable of
            providing GSM Location Area Code/Cell ID location information.</p>

          <p>For location reporting, devices supporting this
            capability return a string in the format "MCC,MNC,LAC,CI" (without the
            quotes of course) where the following applies:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              MCC is the three-digit ITU E.212 Mobile Country Code of the
              network provider to which the mobile is currently registered.
              This value should be the same MCC as reported by the
              org.freedesktop.Modem.Gsm.Network.GetRegistrationInfo() method's
              returned "operator code" argument.
              e.g. "310"
            </li>
            <li>
              MNC is the two- or three-digit GSM Mobile Network Code of the
              network provider to which the mobile is currently registered.
              This value should be the same MCC as reported by the
              org.freedesktop.Modem.Gsm.Network.GetRegistrationInfo() method's
              returned "operator code" argument.
              e.g. "26" or "260"
            </li>
            <li>
              LAC is the two-byte Location Area Code of the base station with
              which the mobile is registered, in upper-case hexadecimal format
              without leading zeros, as specified in 3GPP TS 27.007 section
              10.1.19.  e.g. "84CD".
            </li>
            <li>
              CI is the two- or four-byte Cell Identifier with which the mobile
              is registered, in upper-case hexadecimal format without leading
              zeros, as specified in 3GPP TS 27.007.  e.g. "2BAF" or "D30156".
            </li>
          </ul>
          <p>The entire string may only be composed of the ASCII digits [0-9],
            the alphabetical characters [A-F], and the comma (,) character.  No
            other characters are allowed.  For example: "310,260,8BE3,2BAF" or
            "250,40,CE00,1CEAD8F0".</p>

          <p>If any of these four items (MCC,MNC,LAC,CI) is unknown or the
            mobile is not registered with a network, then the GSM_LAC_CI location
            information item should not be provided as a returned value from the
            GetLocation() method or in the Location property.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="GPS_RAW" value="0x4">
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>For capability reporting, indicates the device is capable of
            providing raw GPS information using a series of defined key/value
            pairs.</p>

          <p>For location reporting, devices supporting this
            capability return a D-Bus dict (signature a{sv}) mapping well-known
            keys to values with defined formats.  The allowed key/value pairs
            and their formats are:</p>
          <table>
            <tr><th>Key</th><th>Value Type</th><th>Value contents</th><th>Example</th></tr>
            <tr>
              <td>latitude</td>
              <td>d</td>
              <td>Latitude in Decimal Degrees (positive numbers mean N quadrasphere, negative mean S quadrasphere)</td>
              <td>38.889722 (ie, 38d 53' 22" N)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>longitude</td>
              <td>d</td>
              <td>Longitude in Decimal Degrees (positive numbers mean E quadrasphere, negative mean W quadrasphere)</td>
              <td>-77.008889 (ie, 77d 0' 32" W)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>altitude</td>
              <td>d</td>
              <td>Altitude above sea level in meters</td>
              <td>33.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>horiz-velocity</td>
              <td>d</td>
              <td>Horizontal velocity in meters-per-second</td>
              <td>.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>vert-velocity</td>
              <td>d</td>
              <td>Vertical velocity in meters-per-second</td>
              <td>.01</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>The 'latitude' and 'longitude' keys are required; other keys are
            optional.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

  </interface>
</node>

